[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
SARA BEERY: So why
are we all here?
Deep learning has clearly
been exploding in society.
Machine learning
generally is something
that, when I started studying it
about 13 years ago, didn't work,
and now it works.
So how many of you here in this
room used AI in the last week?
Yeah, almost everybody,
probably everybody.
And we're seeing massive
advances in everything from
AI-assisted text generation
to 3D reconstruction,
things like NeRF, things like
AlphaGo, generating images,
helping with writing
code, playing games.
This has really started to
touch almost every dimension
of society, and it's definitely
very exciting to see.
And I think that
hopefully, all of us
will learn a lot more about
what that means in this course.
So what is deep learning?
First, I would argue that
one necessary component
of deep learning is the
idea of neural networks.
And these are a class of
machine learning architectures
that basically use stacks
of linear transformations
interleaved with
pointwise non-linearities.
And these have really
been a building block
for a lot of the progress
that we saw in the last slide.
But the other really important
dimension of deep learning
is the idea of
differential programming.
And this is essentially
a programming paradigm
where we parameterize
parts of the program
and then let
gradient-based optimization
tune the parameters to
basically optimize that program
or find some of, at least,
local optimal for that program.
And these two things
together is what
we posit make up deep learning.
And we're really going
to dig into both of them
in this course.
So our philosophy for
this is that breakthroughs
in deep learning have been
driven by a mixture of theory
and practice, and
both dimensions
are really vital for future
progress in the field.
And so along those
lines, this course
should hopefully provide
both a theoretical grounding
in important deep
learning building blocks,
as well as give you practice
implementing, understanding,
and using those blocks.
OK, there's still
a lot of people
in the back who are packed in.
I don't know if there's any
way to come further forward.
If not, we'll do our best.
So the class's coursework is
going to be 65% problem sets.
You'll have five psets.
Each will be about
one to two weeks long.
And then there will be some
combination of pen and paper
or, more realistically,
maybe Overleaf,
as well as code that you
will need to do and submit.
And then 35% of the grade
will be a final project.
And this is a research
project that's
focused on deeper understanding
of some of the topics
that we cover in the course.
You'll be asked to propose
something for that project.
So there'll be an
initial project proposal.
And then the final project
will be a blog post
that's going to demonstrate
novel experimentation
and visualization.
And the hope here is
that I don't know,
many of you-- how many of you
are machine learning researchers
who have already written
a machine learning paper,
as first author, or
anywhere on the author list?
OK, so some.
These days, when you write
a machine learning paper,
more often than
not, you also have
to write a blog post
about that paper.
And that's intended
to be catchy, make
people understand the material,
but really get them engaged.
And so one of the
reasons that we have this
as the format of
our final project
is to reflect on the fact that
this is the reality we live
in today, that in machine
learning research,
being able to write a blog-style
description of the work
that you're doing
and not reduce any
of the technical complexity
or the information
that's given across, but
just do this in this slightly
more visual and maybe
even interactive format is
a really valuable skill, and one
that we hope this can help us
think about.
And we'll allow groups,
but only up to two.
And another
important component--
we are not able to
provide compute.
We may be able to provide
some very limited compute,
but that's TBD.
So do not plan
your final project
to be something where you
need to get state of the art
by crunching a huge architecture
on a bunch of huge data sets,
because it's just
not going to work.
You're not going to be
able to outcompete OpenAI
on this research project.
[LAUGHS]
So this does not mean you
can't do good research.
And it's important
to get creative here.
And I think it's actually
a really valuable skill,
particularly as certain types of
large-scale deep learning become
more and more centralized, to
think about how you can still do
impactful machine learning
research in a way that is not
just "bigger is better."
All right, any questions
about coursework or logistics?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is the
final project expected
to be a mix of practical
and theoretical research?
SARA BEERY: So the question was,
is the final project expected
to be a mix of practical
and theoretical research?
I think it depends.
It depends on what you want to
propose as your final project.
But I think we're pretty open.
What we want is for
them to be innovative,
but that innovation can
be in an applied sense,
or it can be in a more
theoretical sense.
OK, so I'm going to do a
really high-level overview
of the schedule, just to
give you a rough sense.
So today, we're really covering
basic interest stuff-- course
overview, a rough introduction
to what neural networks are
and basic building
blocks, and, particularly
in the context of
signposting, what
we expect you've seen before,
because this is not an intro
to deep learning class.
This is advanced
graduate-level deep learning.
And then we're going to
go into how you actually
train a neural net,
then approximation
theory, some different
architectures, things
like grids, graphs.
Then we'll hear from
Jeremy about scaling rules
for optimization.
And then we'll look at
generalization theory, more
architectures, getting
into transformers.
We'll do a really fun lecture by
Phil called the hacker's guide
to deep learning that I
think is quite useful.
And then we'll
talk about memory.
And then we'll get into
representation learning.
So there, we're going to look
at reconstruction based and then
similarity based and then theory
of representation learning.
Then we'll have a little bit of
a series on generative models,
the basics, how representation
learning interacts
with generative
modeling, thinking
about conditional models.
Then we'll talk about
generalization, and particularly
out-of-distribution
generalization.
We'll touch on
transfer learning,
both from a models and
a data perspective.
We'll hear about
large language models.
We'll have some guest lectures
towards the end of the semester,
and those are TBD.
Then we'll hear about scaling
laws, automatic gradient
descent, and potentially
the past and future
of deep learning,
though I think there's
some discussion as to
whether that's going
to be a different lecture.
And then, I think
kind of importantly,
right towards the end, we will
have class-wide project office
hours where we'll have
a bunch of the TAs
and the instructors
all come, and we
can do open discussion around
projects before they're due.
So the next thing is that we're
going to host PyTorch tutorials.
This is intended for if you're
not familiar with PyTorch,
and you think you
need a refresher.
And we strongly recommend
that if this is the case,
or if you even think it might
be the case, that you attend
one of the two PyTorch tutorials
we're going to offer next week.
So the question is if
PyTorch is a requirement,
or you're allowed to use
any other frameworks.
So you're probably welcome
to use any other frameworks
in your final project, but
some of the problem sets
specifically will
have code that's
already built into PyTorch, and
you're filling parts of that in.
So unless you want
to rewrite all of it
in JAX or something,
which more power to you,
I would recommend
that you definitely
make sure that you are
familiar with PyTorch.
OK.
Cool, so I'm going to talk
about course policies.
And this stuff is important.
And it's also all
on the web page.
But I think essentially,
what we want to touch on
is what our collaboration
policy is first.
So everyone is required to
write an individual pset.
So when you're actually
working on your problem sets,
do not work on something
together and then
both submit the
exact same thing.
You can work on the
actual-- the content,
you can discuss that with
peers, TAs, and instructors,
but the problem
sets you submit need
to be your own independent
and individual work.
And that also applies to
the code that you write.
So you can discuss
the code with others,
but you need to each write
your own code separately.
There was some confusion
about this in the past.
Just make sure that you're not
taking the code someone else
wrote, running it, and then
submitting a pset on it.
You should absolutely not copy
or share complete solutions,
and you also should not
ask someone else, hey, this
is my solution, is it right?
And you shouldn't
do that in person,
and you also
shouldn't ask, Is this
correct? on Piazza or Canvas.
So again, the idea is,
it's your independent work,
your independent thought.
And I think it matters more that
you've gone through that process
independently than
actually getting it correct
because you'll learn from
the feedback on your psets
better if you submit something
that you came up with yourself
and get feedback on it
than if you copy somebody.
And then if you work with anyone
on the pset other than TAs
and instructors, we ask
that you write their names
at the top of the pset.
So if you have a study group,
you're all working together--
we don't care if
this is 10 people.
We don't care if it's, in
this class, 100 people.
But we just want to know
who was working together.
I'd be impressed if you managed
to come up with a 100-person
collaborative group.
So AI assistance-- we
take the exact same policy
about things like ChatGPT
or other AI assistants
that we do with humans.
So it's a deep learning class.
You should be trying out
the latest technology.
The idea is not
that we're teaching
you to ignore what's happening.
But we do want you to treat
them like a human collaborator.
Don't ask them to answer
the question for you.
Just try to imagine from
an ethics perspective
that this is like a
peer in the class.
So don't say, what is
the solution to this?
Don't say, write
the code for me,
because you wouldn't
go to your friend
and say, please
write my code for me.
But you're super welcome to use
them as a discussion partner.
Ask them questions
that are contextual.
Go back and forth.
That's all fine.
But don't treat AI
collaboration as if they're not
a human collaborator.
Think of it that way first.
Is this something I would
ask my friend in the class?
And then just like you
can come to office hours
and ask a human questions
about the lecture
material, clarifications
about questions, tips
for getting started, you're
welcome to do the same
with AI assistants.
Again, you're not allowed
to ask an expert friend
to do your homework for you.
Don't ask AI to do
your homework for you.
If you're ever unclear,
imagine the AI is a human
and apply that same norm.
And if you work with any AI on
a pset, similarly to the fact
that we're writing
with humans we
collaborated with, please
write down which AI
and how you used it.
And, of course, this is
a bit vague, but again,
just kind of honor code.
Any questions about
AI collaboration,
or is that reasonably clear?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I had a
question on the last page.
So can we show our work
to the TAs to [INAUDIBLE]?
SARA BEERY: Yes.
You're very welcome to
show your work to the TAs.
The TAs are not
going to tell you
how to answer the
question, though,
but they will work with you to
help you hopefully figure it out
on your own.
Why are we here?
[LAUGHS] What's the goal?
So what do we want to do?
Why are we all interested in
things like deep learning?
One perspective is that
we're interested in modeling
complex phenomena
in the real world.
What are complex phenomena?
Well, you interact
with them every day,
things like natural
language, images,
or visual data in
general, videos.
DNA, ecosystems are
complex phenomena.
Climate change is a
complex phenomenon.
Why is it hard to model complex
phenomena in the real world?
They're complex.
[LAUGHS] And so maybe
one existence proof
for deep learning as a solution
to modeling complex phenomena--
possibly, we could talk
about the human brain.
All of you are
here at MIT, which
means you're pretty good at
modeling complex phenomena
in your brain, I'm guessing.
So first, today, I'm going
to just briefly go over
how we got where we are today.
This is a brief history
of the field of AI,
deep learning in general.
And then I'm going to
go over what we expect
you have already seen before.
It's OK if you haven't
seen these things before,
but we would expect you then
to go and brush up on them.
So if there's anything that I
talk about, and you're like,
oh, I have never seen
that, we expect that.
That's something you can go look
at some of the OpenCourseWare
courses at MIT, go find lots of
resources online, and pick it up
before you go into this class.
And then I'll also talk
about what we actually
cover in the class.
So a brief history
of neural networks--
and I think a fun way
to go through this
is looking at this on
a plot of enthusiasm
for neural networks over time.
So if we go way back
to 1958, Rosenblatt
introduced the perceptron
in Psychological Review.
And the perceptron was the
first neural network, arguably.
And what this was
intending to do
was recognize or
categorize images.
And the idea was
essentially that you
could take some combination
of representations--
in this case,
particularly pixels--
sum them, put them through
some non-linearity,
and get out a categorization.
And really, we'll see
throughout the course
and even today, this idea
still forms the building block
for most of the deep
learning that we do.
And these perceptrons
are components
in many, many, many
different types
of capacities within
things like ChatGPT.
When this paper came
out back in 1958,
people were incredibly
enthusiastic.
It made waves.
And then in 1972,
Minsky and Papert
wrote a book called
Perceptrons, Expanded Edition.
And this book takes a very
critical lens to the idea
that a perceptron could
be seriously considered
a model of the brain.
And it also carefully and
mathematically describes
and characterizes
the limitations
of what a perceptron can model.
And it did so, so
carefully and so critically
that all of a sudden, enthusiasm
for machine learning really
took a dip.
So in the '70s, we were not
excited about neural networks.
But then in 1986, this book came
out called Parallel Distributed
Processing.
And this was fundamental
because it introduces
the concept of backpropagation.
And this was really
the thing that
enabled multilayer
perceptrons, so not just
a single perceptron,
but actually
multiple perceptrons
stacked on top of each other
to actually be reasonably
trained, reasonably fit,
this concept of being
able to backpropagate
a gradient through multiple
layers of perceptrons.
And what this
enabled you to solve
were things like
the XOR problem.
For the first time,
you could reasonably
solve categorization
problems that
were not separable from
a linear classifier.
They pointed to backpropagation
as a breakthrough.
It led us actually
handle things where
you need multiple different
boundaries and these nonlinear
boundaries to be drawn,
which is only possible if you
have multiple layers
of a perceptron.
You'll never be able
to solve the XOR
problem with a single-layer
neural network.
And everyone got
really excited again.
So in the '80s, yet again,
machine learning was something
that people were pumped about,
and particularly this deep
learning neural network
perspective on machine learning.
In 1998, Yann LeCun put out
convolutional neural networks.
There's an awesome demo
that he has on his web page.
I'm sure many of you
have heard of Yann LeCun.
And this seems
like it would mean
that everyone was really excited
about neural networks again.
But if you go to
NeurIPS in 2000,
this is the premier conference
on machine learning.
It evolved from an
interdisciplinary conference,
which was on basically
the science of the brain
and machine learning to
specifically just a machine
learning conference.
If you look at that
conference in 2000,
the most predictive words
in papers in the title
for acceptance were "belief
propagation" and "Gaussian."
And the title words most
predictive of paper rejection
were "neural" and "network."
[LAUGHTER]
So this is what we
called the AI winter.
And one of the
reasons it was called
the AI winter is because even
though we had the theory,
we had the building
blocks, we didn't actually
have the ability to
train them efficiently.
We didn't have the right
programming perspective,
and we didn't have
the right hardware.
But then in 2012, Alex
Krizhevsky and his co-authors
published AlexNet.
And AlexNet was also another
convolutional neural network.
But importantly, Alex Krizhevsky
was a brilliant programmer,
and Alex Krizhevsky
figured out how
to program GPUs, graphics
processing units, that
have been developed to
handle massive-scale parallel
multiplications for
graphics, for video games,
and for high-resolution images.
But he figured out how to
program those and repurposed
that hardware for the
training of neural networks.
And I can't tell you how much
of a shot heard around the world
this was in our field.
But this, for the first
time, outperformed
every single other
possible method
that was out there on ImageNet.
ImageNet-- how many of you
have heard of ImageNet?
Yeah.
ImageNet was the first
very large-scale data
set of its kind.
And I actually
think that this is
an important
component, what made
machine learning start to work.
And I would argue
that, of course,
it was the theory
and the programming,
the ability to actually
efficiently fit these things.
But the other really vital
component was the data.
Machine learning does not work
without large-scale, curated,
labeled data in many
capacities still,
though we're getting
better and better
at self-supervised learning.
But so all of a
sudden, we were back.
Everyone was enthusiastic again.
And actually, if
you look, these were
hype cycles of about
28 years, both of them.
And so the question is, where
are we going to be in 2028?
So it's 2024 now.
It's 2024, so in four years,
where are we going to be?
So one argument would be, OK,
we're in another hype cycle.
But I would actually argue
that that's probably not true.
Another one would be
that we're just way
off the deep end in
terms of enthusiasm,
and by 2028, we'll be in
some-- out in the stratosphere.
Or possibly we're doing
something like this.
Maybe in 2028,
we're going to hit
some new plane of
enthusiasm, and then
we'll start to
realize limitations,
and we'll oscillate again.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Could AI take
over society by 2028?
SARA BEERY: [LAUGHS]
So the question
is, will AI take
over society by 2028?
My answer is, let's see.
[LAUGHS]
So what's deep learning today?
What are the components
that make it up?
First, I think a really
important one is Autograd.
These are coding languages
like PyTorch and TensorFlow
that give us a really
clever way to do things
like implement the chain
rule in software, making
good use of available hardware.
And this has enabled
us to do things
like approximate the
gradient of any function,
even if it's an approximation.
These are a really important
component of deep learning.
And if you do anything
with deep learning,
I doubt that you're doing
what Krizhevsky did.
I doubt that you're programming
these things from scratch.
You're almost certainly working
with existing programming
languages that are built
for machine learning.
Its billion-plus data point
datasets, things like LAION.
So that scale of data that
I talked about before,
this is an incredibly important
component of all of this.
Parallel training on
thousands of GPUs--
again, this is what
we're looking at today--
billion-plus parameter
architectures,
and this number just keeps
increasing, million-plus
dollar training costs.
So, of course, it's
not public knowledge
how much it costs to train
something like GPT 4.0.
But I would bet it's definitely
in the many millions.
Shockingly good results-- I
don't know about any of you.
I mean, I've been working in
this field now for a while,
and I think we've been seeing
results recently that I didn't
anticipate seeing in my lifetime
from when I started, back when
things didn't work.
So that's been both
exciting to see,
and also sometimes, I think, for
many of us a bit overwhelming,
because you're like, oh,
gosh, the problems I thought
were problems aren't
problems anymore.
So what are the problems?
Of course, I work
in the world of--
I work a lot on
biodiversity loss
at a global scale
using machine learning.
And I would say that
biodiversity loss is definitely
still a problem, and one that
machine learning is sometimes
helping, but often also
hurting, because the carbon
costs of actually training
these models is significant.
But all of these
massive things-- massive
isn't necessary.
So things like Stable Diffusion
are actually pretty lightweight
and were incredibly impactful.
So things don't always
need to be big to be good.
And then I think another
really important component
of deep learning today is
the idea that it is primarily
an open source
community where we have
what we call modular reuse.
So people take weights that were
trained by one person with one
architecture.
They might take that and use
that entire thing as a module
within another,
larger system that
has many different
components that are being
pulled from different things.
Now, I think that this open
source perspective is really
something that's driven a lot
of progress in machine learning.
But also one of
the things that we
have been seeing in
the last few years
is that things are less and
less likely to be open source.
You might have an API,
but you aren't necessarily
going to get the weights and
the architecture for something
like GPT 4.0.
So for the rest of
the lecture, this
is the signposting
I'm going to use.
Looking back, this is what
we expect you've seen before.
The green looking
forward, that's
what we're going to
cover in this class.
All right, pretty
straightforward.
I expect you have
seen gradient descent
before you come to this class.
So gradient descent
essentially is the idea
that we're trying to
optimize some cost function.
And the way we're going
to do that is we're
finding some minimum over a set
of all of our training data,
some minimum set of parameters,
where then the loss is actually
minimized for all of those
different data points.
So what this actually
looks like in practice,
you're trying to find
some theta star, which
is like your optimal
set of model parameters
that minimize your
cost function.
And so maybe you start
somewhere random,
and then you calculate
your gradient.
Now you update the
weights of that model
in the direction of the
gradient, and you step through,
et cetera, et cetera.
And I think many of you have
probably seen this before,
and we'll talk in
an upcoming lecture,
cover some of the different
dimensions of things
like stochastic gradient
descent, et cetera.
But we're assuming that
you've seen this idea before,
probably in intro to ML
lecture, for example.
Covering in this class, we'll go
into a little bit more detail,
backprop and
specifically this idea
of differential programming.
So what does it actually look
like to build programming
languages that are structured
around the idea of optimality
and optimizing through gradient
descent for different components
of that architecture?
And I think one of
the things that's fun
is thinking about what are
you actually optimizing for,
and what are you pushing
the gradients through to?
So here, one iteration
of gradient descent
is essentially
something like this,
and we have some learning rate.
And all of that, we're going
to go into in a lot more detail
next Tuesday where we're
going to be talking about,
where does this
actually come through,
how do we think about what
some of these choices are,
and how we actually
build out the learning
structure for backprop.
I do expect that
you've seen things
like multilayer perceptrons
and nonlinearities, things
like ReLUs, before.
So computational neural network
is often some form of vector
in, vector out.
And this arrow that goes
from vector in to vector
out is a lot of what
we're going to be
talking about in this class.
What computation
does that cover?
How does that
actually build out?
So one cool thing
about neural networks
is that they often are reusing
the same simple computational
units over and over again.
So there's often a lot of
the same kinds of computation
that are being
repeated and reused.
And what these actually look
like, these building blocks
that are being used
over and over again,
they're often some
combination of a linear layer.
So here-- and we will be
sticking with this type
of notation for the
rest of the class--
what we call z sub j, so
some component of this output
representation in
that linear layer,
that would be a sum over i
of some weight times each
of those input components--
basically, pretty simple.
And that can also be written
essentially this way, where
you have some set
of weights, and then
you also incorporate
a bias term.
And this is a term
that does not actually
take in any of those
input components.
It's just a bias.
And that can also be written
in a vectorized notation, which
makes everything
much more simple.
So again, just with a focus on
the notation, that output unit z
sub j is x, that input
vector, transposed times
w sub j, so the set of weights
that correspond to that output
component and that bias term.
And then what we
consider theta-- so
that's all the parameters
of the model-- that's
the set of all the weight
terms and all the bias terms.
So what actually
makes a neural net
a neural net is the
fact that it's not just
linear combinations of inputs.
You also have some sort
of nonlinear function
that is mapping your outputs.
And that's something
like g sub z.
And in this case,
that's something
like a pointwise non-linearity.
So that's an important dimension
that these non-linearities
are usually pointwise.
So one possible non-linearity
would be this one.
g sub z would be 1 if z is
greater than 0, or 0 otherwise.
Is this a good choice of
non-linearity for a neural net?
AUDIENCE: No.
SARA BEERY: Why not?
AUDIENCE: It's not
differentiable?
SARA BEERY: Yeah, so it's
not differentiable, exactly.
And why is the fact that it's
not differentiable not good?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Because it
hinders backpropagation.
SARA BEERY: It hinders
backpropagation.
Why?
AUDIENCE: It makes
the [INAUDIBLE] set
harder [INAUDIBLE].
SARA BEERY: Yeah, so
the directionality.
If you're anywhere
on this graph,
you don't know which
way to go, essentially.
The gradient is zero.
So you can try to take
a gradient ascent step.
You're not going to move because
the gradient is zero, exactly.
So this roughly is called a
perceptron, this linear input
plus a pointwise non-linearity.
And you actually can arguably
do linear classification
with a perceptron.
So if you take a
really simple version
of this where your input is
just two-dimensional, x1, x2,
and you have some w1/w2 learned
weight terms that you use
to combine to get z,
which is your hidden unit,
and then you map that
via a function to y,
you then define z as
x transpose w plus b.
And y is now some
function g of z.
What this looks like
for any set of values
will be something like
this, where you essentially
have almost a ramp.
It's a clear and
standard gradient across.
Why would it look like this?
So why is it smooth and
reasonably straight?
I maybe didn't pose that
question super clearly.
So essentially, the
reason that mapping it
looks like this is
because it's a plane.
So any two-dimensional
version of this
is going to be a plane
with some orientation.
And then very
straightforward, actually,
to turn that into a
linear classifier,
because all you're
doing is taking
some threshold on that plane.
So even a single-layer
neural network
can perform linear
classification
because now this
threshold, that's
basically what that stepwise
non-linearity is giving you.
It's giving you something that
is thresholded at some value.
And so even with
something quite simple,
you can do classification.
Now, that's assuming that your
data is linearly separable.
So if you have training
data like this,
which is linearly separable,
and now you want to find some
optimal set of weights and
biases that will minimize some
loss term where now, again, this
loss is the difference between
the true value-- so here,
the true value is 1 or 0--
and the functional mapping
of the inputs to something
like that value.
If you have something
like this, this
is what we'd call a bad fit.
You have 7 misclassifications.
You're wrong about more
things than you're right.
And all of those
red values, those
are going to give you a high
value in your loss function.
Or you could find something
that's like an OK fit,
less misclassifications.
And maybe this is something
that your model updates to
after a single gradient step.
Your decision surface is linear,
and now you're fiddling around
with what that classifier is--
basically, which values of
weights and biases you need.
And then maybe
after a few steps,
you would find something
that is a good fit, where
you're not actually
misclassifying anything.
So it is possible
to do classification
of linear things,
linearly separable things,
even with something
like a perceptron that's
doing these really
simple thresholding-based
non-linearities.
But like we said,
this actually would
be really difficult to learn.
So instead, maybe you would
try something like a tanh.
So this is another
pointwise non-linearity.
And it was one of the earliest
ones that people looked at.
The things that
are nice about this
is it's bounded between minus
1 and 1, so none of the values
are super huge.
And you get saturation
of the gradient
for super large or
super small inputs.
You're not getting
explosions necessarily.
But also, if you start
out somewhere that's
really far from the
center, you don't
have a lot of training signal
because we're getting close to 0
in our gradient.
And so those
gradients do go to 0
as we go to infinity
in either direction.
The outputs are centered at 0.
So the tanh of z can also be
written as 2 times the sigmoid
of 2z minus 1.
So let's look at what that
sigmoid function looks like.
So in this case, this
is a sigmoid, 1 over 1
plus e to the minus
h or e to the minus--
the notation is wrong.
It should be minus z.
This can be interpreted as
the firing rate of a neuron.
That was one interpretation
of it initially.
It's bounded between 0 and
1, so it's not ever negative.
Again, you have saturation
of that gradient
for super large or
super small inputs.
And all those gradients go to 0.
And the outputs themselves
are centered around 0.5.
So this is kind of
poor conditioning.
It's slightly biased.
In practice, we don't
actually use this.
So instead, in
practice, what we often
use is something called
a rectified linear unit,
or a ReLU.
And this is just
the max of 0 and z.
And this is unbounded
on the positive side,
so it can go all the way to
infinity, which can result in,
for example, sometimes things
like exploding gradients,
because the values
can get very large.
But it's super
efficient to implement.
Essentially, the derivatives
are just that step function.
And it also seems to help
speed up convergence.
So in that Krizhevsky paper,
they showed that they got
something like a 6x speed-up
using a ReLU over using
something like a tanh in
terms of converging that model
and learning.
The drawback is that if you're
strongly in the negative region,
the unit's what we call dead.
There is no gradient,
and so you essentially
have this gradient
collapse, where
you can no longer learn from
that component of the vector.
But this is our default
choice, and it's widely
used in current models.
There's lots of
slight tweaks to this,
but this is really,
really common.
So then the last thing I want
to talk about in this section
is stacking layers.
So we talked about
a single version
of this, where you have
your linear projection,
and then you have
a non-linearity.
But now you can take
that, and you can just
stack another one on top of it.
So now both z and
h are hidden units.
They're somewhere in
the middle of the model.
We don't necessarily--
they're not seen
at the inputs or the outputs.
And essentially,
then, you can also
remember that all
of these things
are stacked on top of each
other, almost in parallel
as well, because all of
these inputs are mapping
to the different components
of the output vector.
And so you have weights for all
of those different dimensions.
So this means that h, our
output of the first layer,
is going to be g, that
pointwise non-linearity, applied
to now instead of vectorized
w transpose x sub j to give us
the individual j-th component,
you can actually just think
of this now as a matrix
multiplied by a vector,
all of the weights for all
of those different dimensions
multiplied by the vector x plus
the vector of all your biases,
b1.
So now you have this
cleaner notation.
And then now y is again g, that
same pointwise non-linearity
applied on top of your
outputs of your first thing,
but now with h, multiplied
by that vector of all
your second-layer
weights and added
with your second-layer
bias term.
And so now, your set theta,
your model representation,
is the set of all of the
different weights from all
the different layers, as well as
all the different biases in all
the different layers.
Oh, thank you.
Oh, yeah.
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: Based off
your application,
how do you choose your
activation function?
What are the parameters of
what might be considered
a good model or, I guess,
a good activation function
based off of what you want
to use your model for?
SARA BEERY: So you're
asking, in practice,
are there any best practices for
choosing the non-linearity based
on different types of data.
I think in the literature,
there's maybe--
you can see it coming out.
But often, people really
do use ReLU quite a lot.
But I wouldn't say that there's
any great general rules of thumb
there.
And often-- yeah.
I would say there's
different things
that people have converged upon
based on experimental success.
So you'll see in the
literature like, oh, yeah,
everything in this line
of work on these data
sets with these things,
they're always using
one or the other component.
And then people build on that.
Sometimes that's called grad
student gradient descent
[LAUGHS] because
you're essentially
writing research papers and
learning from those research
papers what parameters in terms
of things like your activation
functions make sense.
But yeah, I don't know that
I have great rules of thumb
of, oh, for this
type of application,
you should always
use this or that.
Do you?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, it's
not a hard science.
SARA BEERY: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: But it's
usually about what
makes the network more trainable
rather than trying to model
a certain kind of data.
There are a couple of
examples, like using
a sinusoidal non-linearity
to pick out some for you,
if you'd like.
There are a few examples
that do but usually not.
And [INAUDIBLE] does deep
learning has a great answer
to that question.
SARA BEERY: Yeah.
So what Jeremy was
saying is basically,
it's not a hard science.
We don't have
theoretical guarantees
of this is what you should do.
But in practice,
there are-- yeah,
there's counterexamples to that.
So if you know, for example,
that your features are
sinusoidal, it maybe makes
sense to try to pick out
Fourier representations.
You're working in
the Fourier space,
then maybe you should use
a sinusoidal activation.
Anyway, but yes, I wish that
we better understood it.
And that's, I think, why
we need a lot more research
on the theoretical
side of understanding,
how do we actually choose
these things appropriately
instead of maybe learning
everything from scratch
or doing it experimentally,
burning all those trees?
Cool.
So the parameters
of our model are now
all the different
layers of weights
and all the different
layers of biases.
And so like we said, you
can do linear classification
with a perceptron.
But the fun thing is-- oops--
you can do non-linear
classification with a deep net,
even if that deep net is
just a two-layer perceptron.
So here, now we've built a
double-layer model, still
only in two dimensions.
So now we have mapped
through essentially just
this simple non-linearity
in between these two
different layers.
Now if we look at
what this looks like,
that first layer is giving
us one kind of ramp.
The second layer gives
us a different ramp
because it's a
different linear model.
And now if you do this
non-linear combination of them,
essentially what you get out
is you can actually map--
it's almost like think about
the intersection of one ramp
with another ramp.
You get a kind of triangular,
almost a pyramidal component
that will be higher
than everything else.
And so now you can still take
a simple threshold of that,
and now you can get out a
non-linear classification.
And, of course, you can expand
this into many more dimensions.
But this is, I think, some
nice, simple intuition building
as to why you start getting
non-linear models when you're
taking linear combinations,
but with these non-linearities.
Cool.
So another-- so we expect
that you've seen a lot of that
before.
But moving forward,
one of the things
we are going to
cover in this class
is what we can approximate.
So what do we know about
what is possible to
approximate with deep learning?
So one dimension of that
is representational power.
So you have a single layer.
You can do any linear
decision surface.
If you have 2-plus
layers, in theory,
you can actually
represent any function.
And this is assuming,
of course, that you
have some non-trivial
non-linearity
between those layers
because if you don't
have that non-linearity,
it turns out
that a linear layer and
another linear layer, this
is just a linear combination.
It's still linear.
So you need that non-linearity.
But doing that, you can
actually approximate anything.
And one way to
think about it is,
given some amount of
capacity, some number
of different dimensions
that you can do,
you can actually
approximate any function.
This is a rough,
hand-wavy intuition thing.
But as you're shrinking the
size of these different vertical
things, you're getting
something like a Riemann sum.
You can approximate
any integral as long
as you have enough
capacity in terms
of the number of small things
that you're building up.
So this gets at basically one of
the issues, which is efficiency.
So in theory, you
could approximate
any complicated function
with a sufficiently wide
two-layer network.
So this means not two
dimensions, maybe thousands
or millions of dimensions.
But in practice, that's
actually very inefficient.
So a narrow deep
model, maybe something
that only has much fewer
dimensions in terms
of the size of each vector
or each input and output,
but now many, many, many
more stacked layers,
you might be able to, with
a lot less parameters,
approximate the same
complex function.
In practice, we do
find that's true.
More layers helps.
And we'll get into this a
little bit in lecture 3,
which is about approximation
theory, the theory of what
it is possible to approximate.
And then the other
thing that we're
going to cover in this
class is architectures.
So when we talk
about deep networks,
really, often, we're talking
about something that's roughly
like this, some cascade of
repeated simple computations,
each of these linear
and then linear models
with a non-linearity.
And then with every
increasing layer,
we're getting more
abstracted representations.
You're getting a
higher capacity model.
And this means it can form
more complex and abstract
calculations.
Whereas a shallow network, if
it's not sufficiently wide,
it could maybe only efficiently
compute simple things
like maybe finding
edges, a deep network
could efficiently
compute harder things
like recognizing this clownfish
or translating English
to Chinese.
And so this classification
of complex things,
essentially, your
whole function f
of x is now this stacked
or almost chain-like
mapping from your final
layer, which is then
a functional mapping
of your previous layer,
and in and in and in and in,
all the way back to that input.
And there's a lot
of different ways
that we've learned to
build these mappings
for different types
of problems and based
on the structure of the
data we're trying to model.
And we'll get into that.
We'll talk about CNNs, GNNs,
transformers, and RNNs,
so convolutional neural
networks, graph neural networks,
transformers, and
recurrent neural networks.
And then the other
thing that we're
going to be talking
about in this class
is when and why
we can generalize.
So why do deep nets generalize?
Essentially, deep nets
have so many parameters,
they could just act
like lookup tables.
They would just regurgitate
the training data.
But instead, they seem to
learn rules that generalize.
And this actually
defies classical theory.
So the classical
theory basically
says that if your model
is overparameterized,
it will overfit.
There's this capacity
versus risk or error curve
where if you don't
have enough capacity,
you're going to
underfit the model.
And then with too much capacity,
you're going to overfit.
But in practice-- and this
is from this paper "Double
Descent"--
what we see is that in this
modern interpolating regime,
we go past that point of
being overparameterized,
and we're actually then
able to actually pass
some interpolation
threshold or ability
to have enough
capacity in the model
to interpolate between
the data points.
We're actually able to then
potentially get even better,
even though the models are
massively overparameterized.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What do
you mean by capacity?
SARA BEERY: Capacity
is the number
of parameters in the model.
So that's both the
width and the depth,
basically how many values are
captured in those model weights?
Yeah.
Yes, thank you.
AUDIENCE: And how does that
relate to the size of the data
samples that you're passing?
SARA BEERY: Yeah.
So that is not a
dimension on this plot,
but it definitely
is also related.
So if you have--
but it's related
in a different dimension.
If you're learning
from fewer data points,
it's very easy to learn to maybe
overfit to those data points.
So you could think of that
honestly, in another way,
maybe as being a different
dimension of capacity here,
where it's like almost the
capacity of your training data.
But, of course, there's
not a direct translation.
But so if you don't have
enough training data,
you also can't learn to
interpolate between those data
points because you don't have
enough coverage of the data
distribution.
I live in that world a lot.
We often don't have
enough data to learn
a general representation
without a lot of handy tricks.
We will talk about some
of those different tricks
in this class, some
of the different ways
that we try to convince
models not to overfit to data
and try to learn to
generalize beyond maybe what
is captured in the data.
But I think that dimension
is really important,
and it's one of the
reasons that none of this
was possible until we started
building big enough data sets,
where you had enough
coverage of the space
that you wanted to
model in your data
to be able to start
interpolating between them.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Can you just
clarify the difference
between overfitting
and overparameterized?
SARA BEERY: Oh, yeah.
So, I mean, I think
this paper would
be great to read to be
able to really get into it.
But essentially,
the idea here is
that in the previous
literature, we
said that at some point, if
you had too many parameters,
you were going to overfit and
learn a model that actually
generalized worse because based
on the amount of data that you
had, it was going to-- there's a
classical example where you have
three data points.
And if you try to learn a
12-dimensional function,
it will learn something like
this to fit those data points
perfectly.
But actually, it's not
likely to generalize
because it's basically
too spiky or too peaky.
So that's the idea
of overfitting.
But this idea of
overparameterized
is basically instead of saying
underfitting and overfitting,
now we're saying that the new
paradigm is underparametrized
and overparameterized.
And what they're
basically saying
is that you maybe can't
be too overparameterized,
though this perspective
is one that doesn't
take into account resources.
So there's many, many
people and places and places
that are at MIT, but even
actually in this class,
where we don't have
infinite compute resources.
So actually, what
you really want
is some optimal point
on this curve where
you get good performance,
but you're not maybe
using resources
that you don't have,
super, super large memory GPUs.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: When you gave
the example of using
two very wide layers versus
multiple narrow ones,
[INAUDIBLE] there's
a rule of thumb about
which is better for about
the interpretability
between the two?
SARA BEERY: Yeah.
OK, we're definitely
going to get
into this a lot more in
some of the later lectures,
these choices between breadth
versus depth in models.
But at a very high
level, your intuition,
I think, that you're
getting at is correct.
If you have only two layers--
actually, maybe
not, because if you
have two almost infinite
parameter layers,
really, really high dimensional
space is hard to interpret.
If you have lower dimensional
space over many, many different
now stacked versions
of these layers,
it's also hard to interpret.
So I would say like in ecology,
for example, people often
still use just
generative additive
models of a bunch of
different linear things
because they need
the interpretability,
or they feel like they do.
And anytime you get
to larger numbers
of parameters in either
dimension, that interpretability
gets more difficult.
AUDIENCE: I was
just going to add
that even in, let's say OpenAI,
it's a closely guarded secret
what recipe of
width versus depth
that they use in GPT whatever.
If you can come up with
a really scientific way
to answer that question,
you could go and get
a job there and--
SARA BEERY: Make 7 figures.
[LAUGHS]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SARA BEERY: Yeah, so
what Jeremy is saying is,
there's no perfect prescription
or recipe for width versus depth
and what's optimal.
Yeah.
So the simplicity hypothesis
in classical theory
basically says that big models
learn complicated functions
and overfit the data.
And the emerging theory is
that deep networks actually
learn simple functions
that generalize.
And we're going to talk about
this a lot more in a theoretical
and a more experimental
lecture around generalization,
both in and out of distribution.
So again, what I've
expected you to see
before-- softmax,
cross-entropy loss-- basically,
we have this model
that we're trying
to use to learn to classify
something like clownfish.
And we assume that we've seen
some of these really basic loss
functions that we use for this.
So for example, if you have
this as your last layer,
and now you have some
set of categories
you're trying to learn
to categorize over,
the simple version of this
is you take the argmax,
and you say, OK, well, the
thing that's darkest on here
is clownfish.
And then the loss that
you would calculate
is, OK, the actual correct
ground truth label is clownfish,
and then the error between those
two, in this case, is zero.
So it's small.
So you've gotten the
correct prediction.
And then maybe, actually,
the real ground truth label
is grizzly bear, and
you've said clownfish.
Now what you'd want is
for your loss to be large.
So you want some
loss function that
does a good job of punishing
you when you're wrong
and not punishing you
when you're right.
And the way we
actually do this often
is if you assume the net output
is some normalized vector,
then you can think of
this as a probability
distribution over different
possible object classes.
And so what you want this
loss function on the right,
this is called
cross-entropy loss.
This essentially
indicates the distance
between what the model believes
the output distribution should
be and what the input
distribution actually is,
which in this case is what
we call a one hot encoding,
or essentially a vector that's 0
everywhere except for the place
where it's correct,
where it's 1.
And so essentially, it's
just telling the network
to maximize the probability
of the training data, which
forces the output to be a
reasonably good probability
model of the object
class, given the image,
assuming you have
enough training data.
So what this looks like in
practice, you say clownfish,
the ground truth
label is clownfish.
Maybe this is your
prediction, so now the score
is basically saying,
this is how much better
you could have done--
how much better you
could have done,
which is the difference between
the amount of probability
you gave the class clownfish.
I'm putting probability
in quotes here.
It's super important to
know that these are not
true probabilities.
They're scores.
And then that red
is the dimension
that you could do better.
And that's telling you the
direction of the gradient
you want to go in.
So maybe grizzly bear,
you got it correct.
It's grizzly bear.
Now the amount that's left
over is small versus actually
if it's chameleon, and
you're saying iguana.
Essentially, this
thing is normalized,
so if you put a lot more
probability on one thing, then
the correct answer,
then you end up
with a much smaller amount
that now you're looking
at the difference between it.
And basically, the idea with
all of this in deep learning
is you're taking all
these different weights
in your massive model, and then
you're fiddling around with them
until you match the
desired output for all
your training data.
You're basically just
wiggling around all
these different weights.
So you're going through
your training data,
you're predicting something,
you're calculating a loss,
and you're doing this for
many different data samples.
And you're doing
it over and over
and over again until the
model gets everything
right, or as close to
everything right as possible.
We also expect that
you've seen some amount
of parallel processing and the
idea of tensors before this.
So this is the idea that
a lot of this stuff,
because it's repeated
calculations,
you can be done in batch.
So each of these individual
losses for the individual data
points, well, it's all
going to be summed anyway.
So you can do it in
parallel, and now you
can take these batches and more
efficiently calculate that sum.
And so look, you take the same
layer for all three of these,
you can stack them,
and now essentially you
get this matrix that's
features multiplied by images.
And so that's what
your tensors are.
They're these
multi-dimensional arrays,
and every single layer
is some representation
of the input data.
And actually,
everything is a tensor.
A tensor is just a
multi-dimensional matrix.
So you can say, OK, here's our
mathematical representation
of this model.
But you can also just
represent it this way.
You have these vectors of
your different input values,
and now you have
your batch dimension,
which is now this vertical
stacking of all those layers.
And now you multiply that
by your weights matrix,
and you get out your
output, and then
you run that through a
pointwise non-linearity,
and then again, just another
matrix multiplication.
And then you get your
output z2, and then you
take that non-linearity,
and you get y.
So this is why
the fact that GPUs
can do so many
multiplications in parallel
was important, because we can
rewrite all of these models
as just essentially
sets of multiplications.
And we'll go into this
in a lot more detail
as well in the future.
So what we're going
to cover in this class
is how deep networks
represent data.
So essentially, it's
this idea, where
deep networks are a more compact
way of representing knowledge
in data.
And previous methods we saw
were more like lookup tables.
But there's other
and maybe better ways
to learn a mapping
between input and output
that basically assume that there
are these lower-level building
blocks that are useful for many
different possible downstream
tasks.
So one nice example
is the idea of trying
to learn a classifier
for the letter T.
So if you want to learn
to classify the letter T,
you could try to build a
classifier just for the letter
T. Or you could take a
classifier that classifies
lines, and you could
say, OK, here's a line,
and then you could rotate, have
a rotation of that classifier,
and you'd say, here's a line.
And now all you have to do is
understand the connection point
between these two lines.
So that line classifier is
reusable in some combination
to get a T classifier.
And that's the basic idea here.
And actually in
this post hoc way,
we've analyzed what
is learned in layers
of things like convolutional
neural networks.
And we do see that you'll
get low-level representations
in the earlier layers.
Then they get combined
into more and more complex
representations in
those later layers.
And you can actually
see this as well.
If you take an input
image, and you take those,
and you cluster them in some
low-level representation
of the space for each layer, the
layers earlier on in the network
are not going to cluster well by
category, because they're really
just categorizing
things like, does it
have directional orientations
of light and dark gradients
in the pixels?
But actually, when you get
towards the end of the network,
it's learning more
concepts, and that's
where you start getting these
clusters of different things
like fish.
And we will talk about actually
how that representation learns
and is structured through space
in a bunch of different lectures
on representation learning,
where we talk about
reconstruction,
similarity, and theory.
We're also going to cover
generative models going forward
in the class.
And this is things like
text-based and image-based
generation.
And we'll cover basics,
representations,
and conditional models.
And then we're going
to cover in this class
how to think about
weight reuse and some
of the efficiencies
in terms of training
if you're able to
reuse components
of previously trained models.
So here, again, this
idea that, all right,
well, you learned this thing to
categorize pictures of animals,
and now maybe you
want to categorize
some sort of satellite
imagery, well,
actually, a lot of those
initial components about lines
and orientations and
structures, those
are useful for both of these.
So what do we really need to
learn from scratch versus what
is generally useful in terms
of the representations that
are learned?
And this is really
valuable if you
don't have big data
or big compute,
if you can pre-generate
representations that then you
can learn on top of without
needing to learn everything
from scratch.
And so we'll get
into whether or not
these things are
generalizable or transferable
in these transfer
learning lectures,
where we talk about
models and data.
And then finally, we'll
talk about scaling.
So when you think about
the scale of a brain,
something like this little
worm only has 302 neurons,
so you can think of that
as 302 different values
in its neural network.
A fruit fly is 15,000.
Human beings have
100 billion, roughly.
Elephants have 250 billion
neurons in their brains.
I work with elephants a lot.
They're amazing.
And we'll talk about
scale and deep learning
and what this
means, and actually
get into some of the
really great questions
that different people
asked in terms of,
how does maybe scaling rules
change when you're thinking
about optimization, what
are the laws of scaling,
and how do we think
about something
like automatically learning
how to best optimize a model?
Great.
So I tried to cover
today how we got
where we are today, basically
just honestly mostly joking,
but definitely a brief history
of these fluctuation and hype
cycles.
I would say that
everyone's pretty clear
that we're currently in a really
hypey part of the hype cycle.
What we expected you maybe saw
before and also very high level,
some of the things we're
going to cover in this class.
So I'm happy to, if anyone
has any final questions--
yeah.
AUDIENCE: Slightly
underweighted,
but would you be
willing to share
an estimate for how many data
it will take this first lecture
to get a million views?
SARA BEERY: How long it'll
take the first lecture
to get how many views?
AUDIENCE: Let's say a million.
SARA BEERY: Well, I mean,
honestly, the intro lecture
is probably going to
be the least watched
of all the lectures
[LAUGHS] because it's just
a bunch of course logistics.
We might even edit those out.
But great question.
I have no idea.